C.I.N.C no 35201-1389508-5

Aamir Riaz

Consultant, Researchers, Educationist, Columnists & Writer

Key Qualification

Over 20 years of professional experience in consulting & research, acclaimed columnist in various leading news papers and journals on different social and political issues, edited and published different books and providing consultancy to various National and International Organizations including USAID, DFID, GTZ, UNDP, CIDA, Action Aid, Federal Ministry of Education, Provincial Local Government Department etc.

Worked with government institutions & donor agencies

Areas of Strength

- BRIDGING THE GAPE BETWEEN SOCIO-POLITICAL ACTIVISM AND RESEARCH
- QUALITY RESEARCH
- CONSULTING IN EDUCATION & DECENTRALIZATION
- AWARENESS CAMPAIGNS REGARDING SOCIAL AND POLITICAL RIGHTS
- EDUCATION POLICIES IN PAKISTAN AND ITS IMPLEMENTATION
- PUBLIC PRIVATE PARTNERSHIP
- EDUCATION MONTEREY SYSTEM AND PUBLIC PARTICIPATION
- EDITING & PUBLISHING
- COLUMN WRITING
- MONITORING AND EVALUATION

Publications

What We are teaching our Children 2011

Content Analysis of Pakistani textbooks from class 1 to 10 published by PTB in 2010 of four subjects 1- Pakistan Studies 2- Islamiat / Ethics 3- Urdu 4- English The report have an historical background of education from British times explaining public, private and religious education and identifying numerous biases in our textbooks.

Our Girls..Our Future 2013

Identification of images/pictures published in textbooks which promotes gender as well as rural biases

The report identifies images/pictures published in PTB textbooks from class 1 to 10 in 2012 which strengthen biases among students, parents and teachers.

Professional Career

CONSULTANCIES

- 2014: From March till mid-July, Worked with DFID on Text Books Audit of School Books in Punjab
- 2014 till to-date: Working with I-SAPs regarding constituency base initiative for strengthening School Education through political actors in Lahore
- 2013-12: worked with UNFPA on a project "Preventing and Ending Child Marriage" supported by United Nations adolescent girls task force (unagtf)
- 2012: April to November, worked with Action-Aid Pakistan for engaging media, civil society and political parties regarding recommendations suggested in the report "What we are teaching our children" a textbook analysis of PTB books.
- **2012:** June to Sept, worked with **SAHE** on a educational quiz for a renowned private TV Channel GEO
- 2011-12: worked with LUMS "Child Labour and Health" project as consultant
- 2011: Consultancy with DFID Assignment for Influencing Text Book Review Process in Punjab
- **2010-11:** Research Study "What we are teaching our children": Research on Punjab Text Book Board text Books from 1-10 in order to build a campaign for pro-peace curriculum supported by **Action aid Pakistan** under the title campaign for Pro-peace Curriculum in Schools.
- **2009**: Literature review "Democratic decentralization and people's participation in local governance in South Asia-A case of Pakistan" for PRIA/Logo Link

- **2009**: worked with **Asian University for Women** established in Chittagong Bangladesh as coordinator for Pakistan
- 2008: Prepared Story Books for Kids as supplementary books for district
 Faislabad ...a project "Strengthening Decentralised Local Government in
 Faisalabad "Strategic Policy Unit", DCO Office, Faisalabad, Pakistan funded by
 DFID

•

- 2008: July to November, Worked with National Disaster Management
 Authority and UNDP-DRM to carry out research on Government's Disaster
 Management Systems and ways to engage media and District Governments on disaster related issues.
- **2006-08**: Worked with **CCHD** on Government of Punjab Local Government and Rural Development Department's magazine form January 2006 August 2008.
- 2005-07: Worked as research consultant with federal government initiative
 "Mid Term Education Review" headed by Javed Hassan Allay for Federal
 education Ministry as GTZ consultant. Develop first time in Pakistan a matrix
 which reflects view points on key education issues in all government documents
 called education policies since 1947 till to date.
- 2004: Worked with RTI/ESSRA as consultant from February 2004 November 2004 on project in Karachi, Hyderabad, Sukhar, Gawadar and Turbat regarding integrating District Education Monitoring Committees with socio-political groups to strengthen public voice in devolution processes. Also suggested to develop a network of Bar councils, press clubs and nationalist organizations to strengthen education monitory committees.

Some Important Books written/edited/translated

- Our girls ---Our Future: a detail report consisted of pre-partition politics around child marriage
 with special emphasis on Child Marriage Restraint Act 1929 and bold stand of Muhammad Ali
 Jinnah, depiction of women images in text books and some stories by child marriage victims.
 Worked as a head of the team who prepared the report funded by UNFPA and published by
 JAAG in 2013-12
- What we are teaching our kids: Content analysis of Punjab text book board Books supported by Action aid Pakistan and published by JAAG 2011
- Internal Migration in south Asia: Translated & edited by Aamir Riaz & Atta ur Rehman Published by Newline 2006
- Mollana Ubaidullah Sindhi life & works edited by aamir riaz published by Takhliqat books,
- Danstan e Danish by Khalifa Abdul hakeem edited by aamir riaz published by Takhliqat books

• Trilogy for Kids: Three books published by city Government Faisalabad, two written by Brigid Smith and aamir riaz and one translated by aamir riaz. 1-Rainy Day 2-Ganti Khan say aati hai 3-Barish ka din

EXPERIENCE

- Executive Director JAAG initiative for change
- General Manager Publications at ILAN VITAL (PVT)LTD <u>WWW.readings.com.pk</u>
- CEO Newline Publishers
- Worked as CEO Gautam Publishers1993-1998
- Worked as partner in Rohtas Books 1991-3

EDUCATION

- Worked on Pro-Peace curriculum supported by action aid Pakistan
- Research on all education policies from 1947 till to date supported by GTZ
- Public private partnership: working with Public schools and low-cost private schools and link them with union councils and community networks supported by ESRA
- Study of education monitoring committees and link them with civil society supported by

ESRA

• Working with non-formal schools in rural area in order to establish a sustainable ground with the help of local community supported by TVO

MEDIA

- Dawn Urdu Blog: urdudawn.com as contributor
- Dunya newspaper: Writing a regular column on social & political issues
- Writing regular column in www.wichaar.com Washington based Punjabi web portal
- Writer: Occasionally writes for The News on Sunday, Pakistan Today, daily express, weekly HumShari and daily Times
 - Blog: writing a regular Blog at http://punjabpunch.blogspot.com/ from 2008
- Editor Awami Jumhori Forum, a monthly magazine covering socio-political issues with special emphasis on under privileged groups, religious extremism and minorities. www.ajfpk.org January 2002 to date
- DEVELOPMENT VISSION Jan 2007 to 2011 Working as editor in a quarterly magazine supported by OPP/RTI,PURC and Mauwan to Strengthen concept of parallel development models based on community participation in decision making processes.
- March 2006 till 2008 Editor Quarterly magazine of NGO BURGAD publish with the support of HBF

Jan 2007 - August 2008

Coordinator Pakistan - Asian University of Women

The Asian University for Women (AUW), located in Chittagong, Bangladesh, is a unique educational institution offering an innovative curriculum combining the best of the liberal arts tradition with graduate professional training. The program, designed to cultivate critical thinking, communication, entrepreneurship and leadership, seeks the most promising women throughout South and Southeast.

March 2001 – December 2003

Worked as Project coordinator with Jaag Trust in a USAID/ESRA funded project, strengthening school system with public private partnership and integrate primary schools of urban slums in Lahore with the local government system.

January 1999 – February 2001

Worked as Project coordinator with JAAG in a project funded by Trust For voluntary Organizations TVO. Established and strengthened 4 Non-formal schools in the district Sheikhu-pura the Punjab.

1991-1996

Human Rights commission of Pakistan

Worked in Production and Circulation department. Established a network of NGO publications, first time in Pakistan.

1993-2009

Managing Director Gautam Publishers/Azad Enterprises /New Line publishers Lahore Published and produced more than 85 Urdu, English and Punjabi books. Managed 70 book outlets in 18 cities of the country with a circulation of more than 250 titles

Other Contributions

Columnist: as writer writes in numerous newspapers, Blogs and magazines on different issues of vital importance especially education, history, politics, decentralization, gender, left politics and national question.

Member Editorial Board of a quarterly Development Vision. A joint project of OPP & Punjab Urban Resource Centre covering urban issues and development sector.

Edited and translated numerous articles and books.

- 1. "Internal displacement in South Asia" originally published by Sage in English. Edited and translated in Urdu with Atta ur rahman sheikh Published by Newline Publishers Lahore
- 2. Inventors & scientists originally published by Indian Publisher. Translated and edited in URDU published by Takhliqat Books, Lahore.
- 3. Obaid Ullah sindhi, Life & Work. A thesis by Saeed Ahmad originally published by Jamya Millya Delhi in its magazine Islam and Contemporary world. Edited and Published by Takhliqat Books Lahore.

Academic Qualification

.

Masters in Political Science from University of the Punjab.

1993-94

FSc & BSc form Foremen Christen College, Lahore.

1982-87

Matriculation from Don Bosco High school, Lahore 1971-81

Voluntary work

1984-86 Student Organization

Reorganized a group with left orientation Student organization, Nationalist Student organization in the Punjab.

•

Social and Political work in unprivileged communities, in order to organize people, for the struggle of their rights. Areas of work were Pakistan Railway Workshop, Bata pur Area, Pakistan Mint.

1987-89 Nationalist Politics

Member Awami National Party

An alliance of nationalists and progressive forces established under the leadership of Khan Abdul wali Khan, Rasool Baksh Palejo and Sardar Shukat Ali.

1990-93 Punjab Base Politics

Founder member and activist of a Politico-Cultural organization Punjab Lok Lehar PLL. Organized a movement to introduce mother tongue, Punjabi as medium of instruction in Primary schools with the collaboration of numerous NGOs, Punjabi groups and liberal democrats. Organized workshops, seminars, dialogues demonstrations to understand and propagate a liberal democratic agenda in the post-cold war era.

1995-1996 Lahore Research Forum

Publisher and member editorial board of a quarterly research journal covering social science in Urdu language

http://punjabpunch.blogspot.com/2013/04/rethinking-how-our-politics-ruined-by.html

http://punjabpunch.blogspot.com/2013/05/punjab-education-record-in-2013some.html

http://punjabpunch.blogspot.com/2013/05/skill-base-education-essential-step.html

http://punjabpunch.blogspot.com/2013/05/skill-base-education-essential-step.html

Jinnah's Pakistan Myth and reality Published at sept 11, 2012 Dunya newspaper http://e.dunya.com.pk/index.php?e_name=LHR&edate=2012-09-11&page=15

•

Uniform standards in education instead of uniform education system http://e.dunya.com.pk/index.php?page=12

•

As a regular contributor aamir riaz is writing at a Washington based web portal from many years http://wichaar.com/authors/?authorID=8

•

14 august 1947, mountbaitan and the Punjab http://www.express.com.pk/epaper/index.aspx?Issue=NP_LHE&Page=Magazine_Page1 2&Date=20120814&Pageno=12&View=1

•

The real JinnahA.G. Noorani's book sheds some new light on the politics of Jinnah and is invaluable for all serious students of history, By Aamir Riaz

•

http://jang.com.pk/thenews/aug2010-weekly/nos-08-08-2010/lit.htmhttp://jang.com.pk/thenews/aug2010-weekly/nos-08-082010/lit.htm#1

•

The matchless politician, The story of a politician who challenged totalitarian regimes in East and West Pakistan, and fought to transform Pakistan into a true federal democratic country, By Aamir Riazhttp://www.jang.com.pk/thenews/may2010-weekly/nos-30-05-2010/lit.htm#1Revival of qissa,A 7th centaury tale which still has the power to rule the world,By Aamir Riazhttp://jang.com.pk/thenews/aug2010-weekly/nos-08-2010/lit.htm#1

•

IN

MEMORY

OF

LATE DR

MAQBOOL

AKHTAR

LALPURRI

http://www.wichaar.com/news/119/ARTICLE/21578/2010-08-24.html

•

Can we control disasters like floods, earth quicks etc http://www.aajkal.com.pk/news.aspx?img=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.aajkal.com.pk%2Fnews%2F2010 %2F8%2F8%2Feditorial_n1.jpg&w=800&h=1349

•

New Education Poicy: Shifts and Riddles

http://www.jang.com.pk/thenews/sep2009-weekly/nos-20-09-2009/pol1.htm#5

.

The News http://www.dunyanews.tv/newsite/eng/main_category_eng.php?catid=klog http://www.dunyanews.tv/newsite/eng/main_category_eng.php?catid=klog

http://www.humshehri.com/DetailStory.aspx?ID=2000

•

http://www.humshehri.com/DetailStory.aspx?ID=1962

•

Articles written by me in AJForum http://www.awamijamhoriforum.org/contart.php?writer=%D8%B9%D8%A7%D9%85%D8%B1%20%D8%B1%DB%8C%D8%A7%D8%B6&id=107

•

Editorials written by me http://www.awamijamhoriforum.org/cont-artbott.php?writer=%D8%A7%D8%AF%D8%A7%D8%B1%DB%8C%DB%81&id=173

Interviews of prominent personalities http://www.awamijamhoriforum.org/contart. php?writer=%D8%A7%D9%86%D9%B9%D8%B1%DB%8C%D9%88&id=176 Articles written in Wichaar http://www.wichaar.com/authors/?authorID=8 Some Important Books Published Contemporary Issue in Pakistan Studies: An anthology of articles edited and compiled by Dr. Saeed Sahfqat, Instructor Pakistan Studies at civil Services Academy, Pakistan: The Institutional Tragedies: The author Dr.Zafar Igbal Qureshi is an eminent intellectual, ex professor in LUMS and currently Dean of management sciences in FCCollege University Ghubar-E-Zandagi: An autobiography of Dr. Hassan N. Gardezi Pakistan's Atomic Bomb and Search for Security by Zia Mian; articles included in this books written eminent Pakistanis such as Dr. Parvaiz Hodbohy, Lt. Gen. Mujeed ur Rehman, Dr. Inayt Ullah and Zia Mian. Hadood Ordinances: a divine sanction by Asma Jhangir Sindh Observed: A selection of articles from the journals of Sindh Historical society compiled by Dr. Mubarak Ali. Punjab Revisited: Compiled by Ahmad Saleem Mahajar: A story of fifty years (urdu) by Brig. A.R. Saddique Modern Urdu Prose: by M. Safdar Mir Pakistan under Siege: by I.A. Rehman Gautam Budh: Biography by M. Hafeez Saeed Benazir and British Press: by Lubna Rafique Poros the Great: A warrior of the Punjab fought with Alexander at the bank of river Hodyspes (Jhelum) in 327 B.C.

Religions of the World: (urdu) by Azad Sulehry

Pharoon ka Baeta: A novel translated from pushto to urdu written by ex-president and ideolouge of Afghnistan Noor Mohamamd Tarakai

Samarkand: (Urdu) A novel written by Ameen Maloof

Taoon: (Urdu) A novel written by Albert Cameo Trant.Dr. Anes Nagi

Trial: (Urdu) A novel written by Fransis Kafka

.

Kikkar tey Angoor: (Punjabi) A selection of Khalid Mahmood's Poetry

.

Twenty years of united Pakistan: Written by prominent Bangali editor of famous newspaper Itefaq, from Bangla in urdu

.

Political Economy of International Labour Migration: A case study Pakistan by Hassan N Gardezi

Education

1993-1994 University of the Punjab Lahore

MA, Political Science.

1982-87 Graduated from Formen Christian's college, Lahore 1981 Matriculation from Don Bosco High School Lahore